[SPEAKER_00]: When you're looking for a place you'd like to meet, try the public library.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's books and things and lots of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a really cool place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just call 781-395-7950.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll take you to desks that are used for reference and info.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hello everyone, and welcome to Medford Happenings, a show far and about the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: I am John Petrella, and the purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices and to discover city services or businesses you may not have been aware of.
[SPEAKER_03]: And our special guest today is Sam Sednick,
[SPEAKER_03]: And Sam is the director of the Charlotte and William Bloomberg Method Public Library.
[SPEAKER_03]: Welcome, Sam.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you for joining us.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you for having me, John.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: We get right into things, Sam.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the first question, and we are very happy to have you on Library.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a great library.
[SPEAKER_03]: But tell us a little bit about yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Who is Sam Sedney?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I've been kicking around Medford for a little over 13 years now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was originally hired at the library as the head of children's services.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then at some point, they decided to make me the assistant director.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when Barbara Kerr retired in April, they promoted me on up to director.
[SPEAKER_01]: But prior to that, I'm from the Midwest originally.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went to high school in Omaha, Nebraska, and then I came out here for college.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went to Boston University for college.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I fell in love with Massachusetts at that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But my course didn't stay right here for a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: I joined the Peace Corps.
[SPEAKER_01]: I served in the southern African country of Lesotho for two years, and that's where I kind of fell in love with working in libraries.
[SPEAKER_01]: I built community libraries there, and I taught in a high school.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I learned the real value of a library when you don't have resources.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hugely important it lets it opens all sorts of doors for folks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when I got back from the Peace Corps I went to school to get my master's in library sciences and and and the rest is kind of history of kind of My my first professional job was in Haverhill and then on on on to Medford to method and we're very lucky to have you I the library I mean, it's it's incredible what goes on up there and
[SPEAKER_03]: And we're going to get into that as the show goes on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, we will.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're a very busy person.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know, can you describe to us, you know, a typical day at the library?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it, you know, library director, what does it look like?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like, honestly, I am not sure I know the answer to that question.
[SPEAKER_01]: A typical day is all over the place right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have, like you said, there's a lot happening up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we are currently working on a digitization project.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bloomberg Philanthropies has given us a sum of money to take some of our local history stuff and digitize them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So myself and a couple of staff members are doing
[SPEAKER_01]: some metadata ads to the stuff that's been recently scanned.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you go to our website, which is medfordlibrary.org, you can click on local history and you can search the newspaper archive because we put up all of our microfilm scans online.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we're starting a new thing because what we notice is our Medford history, our history room, we had a lot of the old, old stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as we got to a more current area, we really had less and less.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is happening to us now will one day be history.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we are, there's a recording studio at the library, and we are working on recording personal stories from Medford residents about why they're in Medford, what they're doing, their stories, what's important to them, and making that part of our local history collection as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: A normal day at the library, sometimes I'm working the desk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I'm cataloging books or working on a project.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I am in meetings and meetings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But every day is a little bit different, and it's all a joy.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you're definitely hands on, you're all over the place, involved with everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Wherever you're needed.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where I'll be, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And just, you know, when you say digitizing, I'm not a tech type of person, but I'm very interested in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you talking like newspapers from the recent past, or are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: So we don't have the newspaper, because newsprint dies hard and fast if you've ever had a newspaper at home, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So what we had were microfilms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we sent out the newspapers when we got them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Originally they made them into these kind of film reels, and that's what we digitized.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that we did actually send out to a company to scan it for us.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they are sending
[SPEAKER_01]: us digital files back.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're uploading them onto this website so that you can check them out and going from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually been a really interesting project.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a volunteer who is helping us out because when you digitize newspapers it will
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called OCR, and it'll give you a transcript of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think about the columns in a newspaper, the transcript was reading all the way across the newspaper, so it wasn't making a lot of sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we have a gentleman in town who's been volunteering with us.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's a software engineer, and he works with AI, and he's gotten a program to correct the transcripts so that they read correctly, and that's really amazing.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'd be very interested in that, because I love all the
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, the past history, like you said, we always look back, it's the old, but it'd be nice to have, you know, 20 years ago, 25 years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, and we have quite a bit.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, no, that's great, that's great.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, this is kind of just a, I wouldn't call it a silly question, but you know, everyone has certain things they love about their job they don't love, but we'll just stick with, you know, what do you enjoy most?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I have I have two pet projects at the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first is the maker space.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you haven't been to the new building, there is a room that is made for crafting and projects.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a laser cutter in there, there's a vinyl cutter, we do 3d printing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is basically a space to learn how to do stuff with your hands to make
[SPEAKER_01]: weird creations and go from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's one of my favorite things of the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: But my other one is kind of a new thing that libraries are kicking around and it's called the Library of Things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you haven't been to the library, we check out more than just books.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm not talking about like DVDs and audiobooks.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking about we have an inflatable kayak you can check out of the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have tool kits that you can check out of the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: We just got a weed whacker.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you need to trim up the edge of your lawn and you don't have that at home, you can check that out of the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have some kind of silly things.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a ghost meter if you just want to check your house.
[SPEAKER_01]: for the ghost out there, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a lot of great stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is really good stuff, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Honestly, the hottest thing, though, is we have folding tables and folding chairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you're having that party at your house.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they can actually come to the library, check them out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Check out a table.
[SPEAKER_03]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's incredible.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think that's awesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so it's it really is a library with everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean we're trying And growing and growing more and more wow, I had no idea that's something and the maker space I gotta ask you that's
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it open to everybody?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Kate Cherian is our makerspace coordinator.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Kate is there 25 hours a week, which means it's not open the entire time the library is open.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we have a trick for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What we do is something called badging classes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you come up to the library and you take a general safety badge class,
[SPEAKER_01]: and basically we show you how the maker space works and how not to injure yourself terribly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then we let you check out that room.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you have a big project and you need to get it finished and you don't wanna make the mess at your home, you can come in, get your general safety badge and reserve that room for up to four hours to finish it off.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we have like some amazing folks that are doing these big quilting projects and they just need a bigger space to do that, lay out all the fabric.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have all sorts of different projects that are coming in and out of there, and we really, really love to see what people are making.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, there's a lot going on.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's incredible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It really is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think of libraries, you don't think of what you're just talking about, but that's, it's good to know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm sure a lot of people aren't aware of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, now, challenges.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, libraries, and I know this is not just in Method, it's everywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're all facing different challenges.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, what changes, I mean, changes, challenges are you facing, you know, today that may be different from, you know, a few years ago or in the past.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, there's so much more going on.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's gotta be more, I mean, budgets.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, there's gotta be a lot.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a small,
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, library, this is a big production, let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a big production.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I will, I think you'd be hard-pressed to talk to anyone running a library that doesn't say budget is always a challenge, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, yep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So budget is always a challenge, but I think right now libraries are kind of caught in that political push right now where folks are getting kind of up in arms about sometimes what's in the collection or who has access to the collection.
[SPEAKER_01]: We are so deeply lucky to be in Massachusetts because there's a lot more protections around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The governor just signed in a right to read rule that basically says that, you know, people can't just come in and like remove books from the shelf because they don't like it for some reason, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Now there is a process to say like, I don't think this should be in the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: If someone has a book that they're like, no one in the universe should read this book.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a request for reconsideration and we would review that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, is we're serving
[SPEAKER_01]: everybody in Medford, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So something that you might not like to read, someone else maybe does.
[SPEAKER_01]: And maybe it's something that one person feels is uncomfortable, someone else really needs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so what I say to folks about our collection is we have amazing crew of professional librarians developing our collection.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have roles that they're going for, they're collecting for lots of different folks.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you pick up a book and you're like, ugh, this is not for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just returned that book, you don't have to read it, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Come back in and we'll try and match up with something that you want.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, I understand, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there's a civil way, like you said, you can't file something and it's very civil and take a look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we'll review it and go from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: but you know that that is a I think a national challenge across yes many many states and I know like some some states have gotten really all up on it and with regards to like youth where they're like any book that might have any sort of like
[SPEAKER_01]: sexual content in it is pornographic.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so what happens in some of the places where they've like criminalized that is libraries are like we can't have anyone under the age of 18 come into the space because we're afraid of what would happen and that feels terrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like if you've ever come to Medford Library we have
[SPEAKER_01]: gaggles of children in and out of there, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have gaggles of everything in and out of there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, we do.
[SPEAKER_01]: We really do.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no doubt about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we really do have collections built for different age groups, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a children's room.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a teen room.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's the downstairs for the adult services folks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you are struggling to find the thing that you were looking for in the library, come chat with us.
[SPEAKER_01]: We love to show people around.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's good.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have a children's.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have a teen, adult.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the way it should be.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That makes sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they're really cool spaces.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I know they are.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been there.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been in some of the rooms and yeah, very nice up there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, as far as library, you know, resources available to the public.
[SPEAKER_03]: Give us a, you know, a synopsis.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's up there?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's available?
[SPEAKER_01]: So we like to say that you don't actually even need to come to the library in order to use the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: So on our website, at the very top, you can look at our digital resources.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our digital resources include things like you can check out e-books and audio books and movies and everything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: from your home device using your library card, which is lovely, particularly if the weather is bad or you just need a little something extra.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we also have, you know, we have programs that you could like get live resume help by using our digital resources.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you're looking for a job and you need help writing your resume,
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a resource called BrainFuse JobNow where you can get interview support and resume support.
[SPEAKER_01]: We also, of course, have the Makerspace.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if maybe you have a small business.
[SPEAKER_01]: That seems to be, I didn't mean to interrupt you, but that seems to be big.
[SPEAKER_03]: I hear, can you like a little detail?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I hear everyone talk about this and I'm like, you hear Makerspace, Makerspace, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so I actually do the general safety classes for the makerspace.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do 3D printing for the makerspace.
[SPEAKER_01]: But think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have a great concept, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you want to start a small business.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you need to build a prototype.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can design that online and print it out and have that prototype, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: A three-dimensional prototype.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can come to the library and you can use a laser cutter and cut out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I knew someone came in and they had a broken lampshade and they were able to cut out the pieces they needed to fix their lampshade.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's all sorts of things that you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes those things are just to play around, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the makerspace, for me at least, I am a bad crafter, I like to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is to say, I will do any craft you want me to, probably not well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like this on Sunday the 30th, we have a maker fair at the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: So from 1 to 4, we're going to be open.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we're going to have all sorts of craft stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to do splatter paint out on the patio.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you are feeling uncomfortable with the really precise crafts, you can come out and just chuck paint at the wall.
[SPEAKER_01]: I like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I promise everyone can splatter paint.
[SPEAKER_01]: I could enjoy that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, the maker space is really
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of designed around the idea that there are some expensive pieces of equipment that exist in the world and not everybody has the space or can afford to have like a 3D printer sitting at home, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So we as a community resource have pooled our money together.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have this equipment here and it's available for you to come in and use and learn about and explore and we just love opening doors for people, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So maybe you come in and learn about 3D printing and you're like,
[SPEAKER_01]: that is the coolest thing and decide to get your own printer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or maybe you just decide to learn about it and that springs you into a different path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or maybe it starts your small business because you were able to print that prototype with us and take it off and win the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the maker space is really everybody's
[SPEAKER_01]: space to find a path, find a thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's also because the library does take in a lot of donations, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: I say this in our general safety class, I say that all librarians are hoarders and everyone knows that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so anytime anyone's cleaning out their basement, they call up the library and they're like, would you like
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we get cloth and paper and all sorts of different craft supplies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so now we're kind of feeding that back out, letting people come in and use it and make wonderful things with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's really nice.
[SPEAKER_03]: I like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And maybe, you know, method happenings.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think we might be interested in make a space.
[SPEAKER_03]: I got to talk to a couple of people.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, that laser printer sounds like something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Come up to the batching class.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I think they should.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can make little characters.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've got a couple of them to come in.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, we'll go take a look.
[SPEAKER_03]: I like that, I like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, okay, we know you have all this wonderful things, wonderful rooms, all kinds of things going on.
[SPEAKER_03]: How does someone, obviously, I know some of the, because we've looked at a couple of things, and some of them, it's busy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's busy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, you go on the calendar and you're like, wow, this ain't available.
[SPEAKER_03]: So how do you, someone wants to do something, whatever it might be, how do you go about reserving a space or, you know, room at the library?
[SPEAKER_03]: I know some of the rooms, there's some decent availability, but you guys really are,
[SPEAKER_01]: incredibly busy up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: We are incredibly busy up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this will be the trick for everybody, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can reserve any room, any study room.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we have five study rooms downstairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is a little bit bigger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can reserve that a day in advance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can go to our website, which is medfordlibrary.org.
[SPEAKER_01]: And right there, there's a room reservation thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can kind of see the availability, pick a two-hour slot.
[SPEAKER_01]: and reserve it online if you have a library card.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't have a library card or you just, you don't want to do it yourself, you can give us a call.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our number is 781-395-7950 and we will help you reserve that room.
[SPEAKER_01]: So a day in advance on study rooms up to a week in advance on the maker space.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you've been badged for general safety and you know how not to cut your fingers,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can come in and use that space.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then like the one that's huge, so Bonsignore Hall is the big room.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the tricky one.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a lot of different programs that are in and out of there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to reserve that room, there are sometimes times where you can get in there and have your own program or have your own thing going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The trick with that is we publish a newsletter quarterly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, our fall newsletter just got published in August.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as soon as our newsletter is published, then we open up the available space to anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, figure out our newsletter schedule.
[SPEAKER_01]: August 1st is for fall.
[SPEAKER_01]: November 1st is for winter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And February 1st is for the spring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, call around that time and you'll have better luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the newsletter, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that available?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, online?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In print?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's available online.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can go to our website and subscribe, and they'll email it out to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't want to do the online thing, we do have it printed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so just stop on by the circulation desk.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's available.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's available right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nice and easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we have all of the programs for the next couple of months in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so you can see what there is to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're signing up for any of the programs, because the programs get full quick too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it's the same situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the first of the month, you can sign up for the next month's stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So on September 1st, if there's any October programs you'd like to get into.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when to get into them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do it early.
[SPEAKER_01]: 9 a.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: is a good time to sign up.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know.
[SPEAKER_03]: We looked at something and we're still interested.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll eventually get in there.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yeah, it does.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's pretty busy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Certain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very busy, which is a great thing, I guess.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a wonderful thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's what it's there for, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: For everyone to use.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's getting used, which I love.
[SPEAKER_03]: It really is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, another thing, I heard you mention volunteers earlier.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you have volunteers?
[SPEAKER_03]: You use them?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you get them?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you look for them?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you looking for?
[SPEAKER_03]: the whole show.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: We do have volunteers.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a form on our website that lets you sign up to volunteer and basically it sends us an email and tells us that you want to volunteer.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's three main categories for volunteers at the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first is if you just want to put books back on shelf for us.
[SPEAKER_01]: We love folks that want to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: We teach them how to take the carts out there and reshelve our books.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So a lot of folks are doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They take an hour or two every week and come in, help us out at the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we really appreciate those volunteers.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are volunteers needed for our new local history digitization projects.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that one's a little bit steeper in training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, if you scan a picture from the 1900s,
[SPEAKER_01]: you have to type in what it's about, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to explain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we're basically adding some notes and things to some of the things that we're putting up online so that it's easier for folks to find what they're looking for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that is an area that we're looking for volunteers.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then of course, because the Makerspace has, like there's so many different types of skill sets that are in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are someone who's a maker crafter and you love sharing your art and teaching others how to do something, we also take volunteers who are like, you know, I wanna teach people how to knit or I'm gonna teach you how to carve a spoon or what have you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have a skill that you wanna share, we'll try and get you rolled into maybe doing a class for us or teaching a program.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another way to volunteer at the library.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very nice, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So in other words, I could probably go up there and scan the picture, but you wouldn't want me because I type like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it could be quite a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll find a place for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm sure you will.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm just saying to myself, you know, I'm the
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm one of those, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, we have like the old I think it was it was from the Mercury.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was their their photo morgue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when they closed down, it's all these old photos.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're all from the like 70s and 80s.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have those.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have we have several boxes of them and they're they're uncataloged at this point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so we are really going through them and just being like, do we know who this is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we like put something like because it doesn't have information on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just in like subfolders.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be like kids.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sport.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's a, yeah, it's a kind of an, that would be something.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you need someone to identify them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if you want to come.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I can do that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know all the people?
[SPEAKER_03]: I know some of them, I'm sure, from back then.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Mercury, that's incredible.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you actually have the physical pictures?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we have the physical pictures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, we're working on trying to scan them so that they are easier to see, but we do, yeah, we have.
[SPEAKER_03]: If I may ask, how did you come about, where do you find this stuff?
[SPEAKER_01]: I like, everyone knows when they're clearing out their space to drop it at the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really like, that's what happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: They come to us and they're like, hey, what about this?
[SPEAKER_01]: And we're like, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh yeah, that's a pretty nice find having those pictures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they're interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's one picture, it was in the kid folder, and it is just a homemade Halloween costume in the early 80s probably.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is like a robot that's like cardboard box, and like vent sleeves and everything, and it's so perfect, I love it so much.
[SPEAKER_03]: So there's some great ones, I'd love to.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be a very interesting thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I would enjoy that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so, you know, we talked about a lot here today.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, I always, anything, you've mentioned a lot of things coming up, you really have.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's any like special things upcoming that you would want people to know, events?
[SPEAKER_03]: I know, I got to say this, I have my library card and there is a library card drive.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's a big one.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you don't have a library card,
[SPEAKER_03]: Get one.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's well worth it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't care if you only use it a few times a year.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's worth it to have it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's nice to be able to go in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the average cost of a hardcover book is $30.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you read one book a year, you're going to make that back with that card.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, there's lots of other stuff you can do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: In September, the Friends of the Library are going to help me out, and we're going to be
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to be canvassing out in the Wellington area because they're the furthest reach from us.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we have slightly fewer households with library cards out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so we're going to come by.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so if you're out there in the Wellington area and we come knocking on your door,
[SPEAKER_01]: We're just there to ask you to get a library card, tell you a little bit more about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you already have a library card, poke a friend in a neighbor, let them know that they should get a library card, come visit us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because we really do, you know, your taxes support our library and we want everybody to get their money's worth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't take that much to get your money's worth out of our library, but that card will get you there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a great thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right, so I want to go through some of the things now.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know we talked about the Mystic Makerspace.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's incredible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Lunch and Learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so we have a senior advisory board.
[SPEAKER_01]: So folks that are 55 plus design programs for other seniors.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Lunch and Learn is on Thursday, November 12th.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically, they're going to have a lecture about Italian-Americans.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they got some food from one of our local restaurants coming in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so you can sign up, learn about Italian-American culture, have some delicious Italian-American food.
[SPEAKER_01]: All at the library.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm all set.
[SPEAKER_03]: Italian-American.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can come and teach our lecture.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I love Italian food.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm a senior citizen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Three out of three.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to be there.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the program for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_03]: I like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Lunch and learn, everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: Remember.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can sign up for that starting on October 1st.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when to get your name on.
[SPEAKER_01]: October.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then I know coffee and books.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's that all about?
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, see, we're just trying to feed everyone for free.
[SPEAKER_01]: So coffee and books, we get donuts and coffee for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So really, that's all you need, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can come in and you'll have to hear me up talk some of our brand new books.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we take some of the books that we just got in from our dealers.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so if you're looking for the latest, hottest, and greatest titles, we'll run through a list of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a real chill hour of some of the fun new books that are coming out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Coffee, donuts, new books.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sounds wonderful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you're always trying to stay ahead of the trends, it's a great way to catch what's coming out.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's very nice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And another one is Black Dahlia.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's a terrifying story for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's actually the Medford Historical Society.
[SPEAKER_01]: So as a community partner, the Medford Historical Society does a monthly lecture at the library.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I wasn't even aware of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know, we have a few more seats than they do in their house.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they come out and do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so they're coming out on September 30th to talk about Black Dahlia and the history of Elizabeth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so it'll be a good chat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are pretty amazing programs.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're good at filling up Bonsignori Hall.
[SPEAKER_01]: They get like 80, 90 people to some of those programs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm sure that's got to be an interesting
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, it's an interesting case.
[SPEAKER_01]: It never got solved right?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I know everyone's Twisting around about it one of those mysteries Come pet this yeah, so We occasionally have some therapy dogs come to the library.
[SPEAKER_03]: I could use that too, by the way
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Jojo the beagle is one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hangs out in one of our study rooms.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you just need to take a break and take it down a notch, Jojo will sit with you and you can pet him.
[SPEAKER_01]: We definitely have folks that maybe are afraid of dogs and want to get used to them come out for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have folks that just want to unwind and have a friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: We also have a therapy dog that comes up to the children's room that's called, it's a reading dog, and it's reading with Ryan.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's for kids that are just learning how to read and need an unjudgy partner to read to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you are someone who's practicing reading, Ryan will sit there and listen to you as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's a couple different therapy dog programs where they come in, and it's a great way for folks of all ages to have a friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a nice program, really nice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And of course, the library card drive.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going to mention that one more time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, if we show up at your door, we have a really cool postcard that we're going to be handing out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you aren't home and you get a postcard from us, it's just us saying hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you already have a card, congratulations.
[SPEAKER_01]: You win.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you don't have a card yet, come on to the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have cool things to show you.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm also going to mention that I heard a jingle.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that is a great jingle.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe we'll get them to write, because we're looking for a new jingle for Method Happenings.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that was a really good jingle.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're going to play it at some point during the show or at the end of the show, but I got to definitely, I mean, I'm going to try pronouncing their names, okay?
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll give it a shot here.
[SPEAKER_03]: If there's anything, you can correct me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Scherzer, Walter, Dimmick, and of course, Joe Hogan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so we had, I was very jokingly talking about coming on Medford Happenings, and I was like, I need like something catchy.
[SPEAKER_01]: We got to make it go viral.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was joking that I needed a library jingle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then two of our library teens came through for me, and they created,
[SPEAKER_01]: the best library jingle song ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So thank you to Shirsa and Joe.
[SPEAKER_01]: We really appreciate their work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I guess Medford Happenings would love a jingle too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we're looking for a jingle.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'd be perfect.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love what they did.
[SPEAKER_03]: That little jingle's great for the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't know of this for sure, but we had a digital music program at the library for teens, and so maybe one of them went to that, and that's how they got their skills.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or they're just amazing, one or the other.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, no, yeah, I mean, it's a great song.
[SPEAKER_03]: I didn't know...
[SPEAKER_03]: You have a digital music program?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so we had Mr. Green come in and do that program for us and teach youth how to use the equipment at the library to make songs.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've had podcasting programs at the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, there's like a recording studio in the tech lab.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so yeah, there's lots of weird tech programs up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you know, you can come
[SPEAKER_01]: Print print a 3d print Rock out with your rock bands Eat it Italian lunch pet a dog And then much to do and then take home the kayak because it really is the biggest piece of equipment I don't want it in my back room.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's something else I mean, I guarantee you people you know that watch the show.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm sure you might yeah, you might have some people come and pick that up now so
[SPEAKER_03]: So when I come for the Italian food, right, is there takeout available?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just bring it back.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know that it'll last that long.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll clear out.
[SPEAKER_03]: I hear you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sam, you know, it's that time again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Unfortunately, we got to close it out.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I really want to thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Big thank you to Sam Sednick, director of the William and Charlotte Bloomberg
[SPEAKER_03]: Method Public Library.
[SPEAKER_03]: You shared great information about the services, resources available at your library, and we wish you nothing but continued success.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a great, great thing you're doing up there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It really is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, before we close out, I want to take a minute to thank everyone who has been watching the show, and I especially want to thank you for your feedback.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're getting a lot of feedback, and it helps us out.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you would like to appear on the show, you can contact us at Method Happenings, 02155,
[SPEAKER_03]: at gmail.com.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you for contacting us.
[SPEAKER_03]: We have a few more shows coming up just from people that have contacted us, so that's great.
[SPEAKER_03]: You'll be able to watch replays of this program on Method Community Media Access Channel.
[SPEAKER_03]: and you gotta check out our website methodhappenings.com you can either view us listen to the podcast of this program uh... this is getting longer and longer every week you can also find all of our shows on youtube just go to youtube.com search for method happenings and please like and subscribe to our channels our videos
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can also now find us on Facebook at Method Happenings.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we also have our own subreddit, which I'm learning about.
[SPEAKER_03]: I never knew about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can find us at reddit.com slash R slash Method Happenings.
[SPEAKER_03]: So for the Method Happenings team, Paul, Marco, Bruce, James, and Joseph, I'm John Petrella.
[SPEAKER_03]: Remember Method.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stay informed.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, everyone.